I can tell just by looking at you then
you're smart
how lewd idea do you think you would be
if I said you're going to do one type of
exercise training the rest of your life
never anything different it's obviously
absurd right but for some reason we
think like that's a good idea when it
comes to nutrition right we're gonna eat
this many grams of protein this much fat
this much carbohydrate and that's what
all of us should do regardless of what
we're doing with our exercise training
or other parts of our life and obviously
that's completely absurd and so I don't
teach in my nutrition classes specific
numbers de what I teach is concepts and
the reason is I believe in an approach
that's called periodized nutrition so in
this video I'm going to walk you through
the concept as well as how to apply it
and it will of course include very
specific numbers for how much protein
fat carbohydrates to eat for things like
gaining muscle losing fat peak
performance and even in the offseason
you excited let's go now before I do
this really quickly I have to give
credit this is not my concept lewis
burke and her team out of australia's
fantastic work here another thing i need
to acknowledge there are a lot of
different ways to do it and i don't
necessarily do these ones at all times
but this is a good example so i would
encourage you not to memorize these
numbers but just think about the
concepts and the logic behind it and
then apply appropriately and modify
based on your context in your situation
so i know i'm asking you to do what
people hate the most in this world and
think alright there's also other things
like carb cycling back loading and then
there's a whole other array of different
ways to play with this but this is i
think the easiest way to understand from
from the very beginning so i'll just
teach it like it's the period ice
nutrition approach so basically what
what lewis and her team i assume their
goal was is to say hey look we do need
to modify how we're eating based on
different types of training and so what
I've done is I've shown you I'm gonna
show you go through four different
theoretical goals gaining masters in fat
in competition probably in the middle of
like competition season or say you got a
hard
wrestling tournament or you're competing
three or four times in a week or
something like that
and then non competition so this could
be immediately after the season or
whatnot and then at the top of course
I've got the different macronutrients
and I'll show you how these things break
down so we'll start off there very first
category a muscle game so what do we do
with our fat well most of the time I
actually feel like these numbers are
pretty solid oh and by the way these are
my numbers I use not necessarily what
they've originally published in there
great research on periods nutrition so
these are ones I like but they're pretty
close usually so some on the
neighborhood of a gram per kilogram in
terms of fat so if you're a hundred
kilogram person you'd be 220 pounds
you'd be eating like a hundred grams of
fat or so a day maybe even a little bit
less is totally fine there of course you
can go higher yes you can go lower but
these are the numbers that I like to
stick to when it comes to fat loss
though this is and I've explained this
in a bunch of different videos even a
five-minute version if you want to just
go quickly take a look at how much I
think it's gone how much protein fat
carbohydrates to eat something like that
I do find carbohydrates and fat are the
easiest ones to reduce when you're
trying to reduce calories so because of
that I don't want to drop fat way off
the earth I don't want to go from a
hundred grams a day to 20 grams a day
you're crazy like that but I just want
to keep it on that lower end of the
limit maybe even a little bit lower not
much more though right so we're not
talking crazy reductions in fact this is
a major mistake folks often make with
fat losses they just cut calories way
too low way too fast so I go from eating
four eggs for breakfast the morning to
eating too we've cut your calories in
half that's a really bad idea so to keep
at the lower end of the spectrum now
when you're in the middle of competition
phase in season or got a lot you're just
competing or training really really
really hard this could be fight camp as
well for those fighting the athletes
that I work with we're gonna go give me
the same or two D even almost double
this number so we can get really really
really high with fat simply because
their calories need to increase and fat
is a fantastic source of calories helps
us absorb fat or absorb vitamins it's
really important for hormonal regulation
and a bunch of other stuff so we will
sometimes go way way way way up on that
if we just need workout
and then of course when we come back off
of non-competition we're to go back down
again and that's just simply because we
don't want to continue to eat like we're
in season we leave the season or else
we're gonna give fat and yes I'm sorry
keto friends but if you overeat fat
guess what it vanishes in thin air and
nothing happens right come on now come
on no it's not magic
moving on to our next category here
carbohydrates this is the range I like
to stick to in general is four to seven
grams and I found it actually works
pretty well from muscle gain as well so
I don't usually deviate from that we
will increase their calories but we
don't need to go crazy numbers here we
don't need to be going to you know 900
grams of carbohydrate a day to simply
gain some muscle you'll probably blow
your stomach to pieces with the fiber if
you're not careful there fat loss no
we're gonna head to down now again
notice we're not dropping carbohydrates
off the table we're not going no carb
you can if you want but you don't have
to there's no good reason to think you
have to reduce carbohydrates that much
if you want to lose fat you just simply
have to reduce calories they got to come
from somewhere
I don't like pulling them from protein
so I don't necessarily drop too much fat
I don't necessarily drop too many
carbohydrates
I just keep both at the lower end of
those spectrums maybe slightly lower
this is not a huge adjustment I mean if
you're going from five grams of carbs
per kilogram body weight you go from
five to three this is very manageable
you don't want to go from seven grams
does one you're gonna feel terrible and
you just don't need to do it and so we
just end edge these things down a little
bit lower a couple of bites less here as
you know a couple of portion sizes just
crunch down just a little bit again
we're talking small reductions here at
most in competition depending on what
sport our tabular urine I mean you can
go nuts with these things especially at
the competitions short-term now I
wouldn't recommend going to fifteen
grams per kilogram of body weight if
your season is eight months long like a
baseball season or something you're
gonna get fat right not because cars
make you family because calories do if
you triple your calorie intake of
carbohydrates and you're gonna add more
weight
the 7up 2:15 is more of something like
an extreme endurance event that's
lasting Tour de France or you know
something like that but for the most
part if I'm say in a short competition
window say we got Olympic Trials and
we're gonna wrestle you know potentially
five to six times over the course of a
week and weights okay then we are gonna
want to go really high in carbohydrate
okay now if we got to make weight we
will actually lower protein and lower
fat lot but we're gonna keep the
carbohydrates really really high if
you're in a sport where weight don't
matter and you can afford to just go
nuts your carbohydrate and you are gonna
compete multiple times in a queue or
three-week span you define going pretty
high in your carbohydrates and it won't
have a negative result and then of
course once we leave season we've got to
come back down you'll see these numbers
match up pretty well with the fat loss
because I've looked really what we're
doing I were presuming post competition
here in our non competition phase our
activity levels have gone way down and
so our food needs to come down with it
as well we see this classically there's
a phrase that is potentially sensitive
so I won't use it but classically with
folks who maybe played a sport or two or
three in high school get to college
don't do it anymore
but yet they continue to use the same
eating patterns it's not like your
metabolism or your hormones shifted that
dramatically from age eighteen eighteen
point five all right don't change that
much what happens is your physical
activity just plummets but you continue
to eat all of the carbohydrates and fat
like you've been eating as a 16 17 18
year old is playing all these sports and
so you tend to UM plump up a touch you
know what I mean so in terms of protein
here muscle gain honestly I don't really
ever go that low in terms of 1.2 I'm
probably never gonna recommend less than
1.5 and I mean to be totally honest if
so is one of the gain muscle I want them
probably and at least 2.2 grams per
kilogram which is one gram per body
weight and all even a lot of times go
higher 1.5 and so what would that mean
on your slide that would mean instead of
one point two to one point seven
probably even closer to maybe three
grams per kilogram you know to two and a
half at the 2-minute to at the least you
can go pretty high there and II know the
rule again you can watch that protein
video
any of my hypertrophy videos to
understand the specific actions of
protein take on the muscle gain in terms
of fat loss now this is a sneaking one
and I will cover this in my family's
videos but you don't want to go over
here in fact I typically go up really
really really high it keeps you full
very long keep some muscle around which
is important to keep your basal
metabolic rate up nice and high it's not
that big of a jump but it's a little
jump and every little thing counts I
need you to feel great you can look at
Jose Antonio's fantastic work but
they've shown pretty clearly if you go
really high on protein you don't have
any problem losing weight and so even if
you over eat a little bit and you're
trying to lose fat protein is the one to
overeat and it's pretty clear right so
I'll keep that number pretty high
it also doesn't make people feel like
they're starving all day which is really
hard if you're trying to lose weight
especially for more than you know like a
week especially or even a month you
don't want to be deprived as scarce that
long any competition though depending on
the competition all go down why again if
it's an eight month baseball season I'm
not going down on protein but other
sports that are maybe a month or two
shorter yeah okay might help us with a
little bit of muscle damage but what we
really care about in season is energy
and competition and so if I can't afford
to go up in calories or you know food in
the stomach I want to keep those carbs
really really high and even fat
potentially high and so I will go down
and protein the same like in literally
like the middle of a race I don't need
protein in the middle of a race what I
need are carbohydrates for the most part
or competition the middle of a game
and so this is the one time where I will
take protein down low or even lower
could be a lot lower than that actually
just because if we need to make sure
we're hedging a lot of carbs in the
system to recover or to be able to train
again compete again whatever we're doing
and again this is really difficult
because depending on the sport it could
change pretty drastically but then a non
competition we're going back up right
keep full keep it covered stay nice and
healthy so here are the specific numbers
for you if you like concepts better
which I like to encourage I've kind of
changed it and do some arrows and you
can just see we're basically doing so
we'll just run through each category one
more time really quickly and then we'll
get you out of here so if
muscle gain we're not really changing
fat that much but we're going what you
know go on
oops sorry we're gonna go make sure our
carbohydrates are nice and high and you
can either keep your protein where it is
or go up a little bit but really you
could have us I should probably change
that first arrow on the fan third but
you could even have a little modified
increase in fat if your muscle good
section as well for fat loss though
maybe a little bit of change in fat but
not necessarily a ton probably dropped
the carbs and keep the protein nice and
really high in competition a lot more
fat a lot more carbohydrates than either
don't move or drop your protein and then
when we get out of competition again
make sure the lower level of that fat
drop your carbs quite a bit and then
keep your protein nice and high so
that's it again that's periodized
nutrition there's a ton of other ways to
do it just want to highlight how you
should think about food and how you
should alter it based on what your goals
are and what your adaptations that
you're searching for what else is going
on in the person's life and how they're
feeling so just some starting places
hopefully enjoyed that if you want to
learn some more about any of these each
individual topics you're welcome to see
any of my five-minute or my 25 or sorry
this is 25 or my 55 minute versions and
now most of you especially my students
are probably happy because you like to
hang I signed up for a 25 minute video
here and we're out of class early today
all right thanks for all the love of
support it's crazy when I look at the
numbers it's like a 99% positive comment
and thumbs up thing on YouTube which is
absurd so thank you so much I really
appreciate this is the best way to
continue to get this quality
scientifically based information out so
thank you for doing your part I'll
continue to do my part and make these
videos and I appreciate you helping me
share the message and post these things
around alright go get your food on go go
good lunch go have some vegetables or
meat or whatever you want or ice cream I
don't really care
okay tell you mommy little bit that I'm
good that's good tell you mom you like
yeah
[Music]